Guide to the Rosalind Howe Sturges Allen Papers, 1928-1999
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Rosalind Howe Sturges Allen Papers
1928-1999
Howe, Rosalind
15.6 cubic feet (22 boxes, 19 map folders, 2 framed items)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Research materials, sketches, drawings, published materials, and exhibition materials relating to Rosalind Howe’s work as an artist and architectural cartographer as well as professional correspondence, published materials about Howe, and published materials which included Howe’s work.
Biographical Note
Rosalind Howe Sturges Allen was an artist and architectural cartographer who pioneered the use of anachronistic maps which featured the architectural history of a place rather than its geographic features. She was born in 1907 to Mary Locke and Wallis Howe and graduated from Vassar College in 1928. She died in 1999.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes research materials, sketches, drawings, published materials, and exhibition materials relating to Howe’s work as an artist and architectural cartographer. Also included is professional correspondence, drawings, paintings, and other artwork created by Howe, as well as published materials about Howe and published materials which include Howe’s work.
Related Materials
The Vassariana Collection contains published Vassar maps.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Maps, pictorial; Wellesley College--Maps, pictorial; Old Sturbridge Village--Drawing (visual works)
Subjects:
Architectural historians; Women cartographers; Women artists; Folder Maps, pictorial
Places:
Annapolis (Md.)--Maps, pictorial; Worcester (Mass.)--Maps, pictorial; New England--Maps, pictorial; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Maps, pictorial; Princeton (Mass.)--Maps, pictorial; Hingham (Mass.)--Maps, pictorial; Nantucket (Mass.)--Drawings; Rhode Island--Drawings; Westminster (Mass.)--Drawings; Providence (R.I.)--Maps, pictorial; Chestnut Hill (Philadelphia, Pa.)--Drawings (visual works); Rittenhouse Square (Philadelphia, Pa.)--Drawings; Blackstone River Valley (Mass. and R.I.)--Drawings (visual works); Bristol (R.I.: Town)--Drawings (visual works); Deerfield (Mass.)--Maps, pictorial
Document Types:
Correspondence; Drawings (visual works); Maps (documents); Notebooks; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Maps; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Adrienne Turner, September 2008. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, May 2023.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Browne, Philemon Sturges, Helen Nader, and Rosalind Waters (M2001-015).
Additional gifts were made by Elizabeth K. Allen in 2010 (M2011-019) and 2018 (M2019-011), and Pamela Hatfield in 2011 (M2011-031).
A framed reproduction of Howe's "An Anachronistic Topography of Vassar Female College" was transferred from the Vassar College Office of the President in 2022 (A2022-001).
Series List
- Series I. Vassar College, NY, 1928
- Series II. Wellesley College, MA, 1943
- Series III. New England, 1976
- Series IV. Annapolis, MD, 1964
- Series V. Blackstone Valley, MA, 1988
- Series VI. Deerfield, MA, 1983
- Series VII. Hingham, MA, 1980
- Series VIII. Nantucket, MA
- Series IX. Princeton, MA
- Series X. Sturbridge Village, MA
- Series XI. Westminster, MA
- Series XII. Worcester, MA, 1981
- Series XIII. Cathedral Village, Philadelphia, PA (senior living facility)
- Series XIV. Chestnut Hill, PA
- Series XV. Philadelphia, PA, 1958
- Series XVI. Rittenhouse Town, PA
- Series XVII. Up Country, PA
- Series XVIII. Rhode Island
  Wallis E. Howe created maps for Bristol and Newport. Prints are included in this series. It may be possible that there is additional material relating to this Wallis's work in this and other series.
- Series XIX. Notebooks
- Series XX. Miscellaneous Materials
Series List
- SERIES I. VASSAR COLLEGE, NY
  - Drafts (Folder 12.12)
  - Published Materials: "Our Fifty Years," VC Class of 1928, drawings of Vassar College buildings, circa 1978 (Folder 3.01)
  - "An Anachronistic Topography of Vassar Female College," color lithograph, 1928; [5 copies] (Folder M1 (Oversize))
  - "An Anachronistic Topography of Vassar Female College," color lithograph, 1928; [framed] (Framed Storage 2.6)
  - "An Anachronistic Topography of Vassar Female College," color lithograph, undated; [reproduction, framed] (Framed Storage 2.4)
- SERIES II. WELLESLEY COLLEGE, MA
  - Drawing, Pre-1945 (Folder M10 (Oversize))
  - Published Prints, 1943 (Folder M10 (Oversize))
- SERIES III. NEW ENGLAND
  - Research Materials (Folders 3.05 - 3.10)
  - Research Materials (Folders 11.10 - 11.13)
  - Research Materials (Folder 19.03)
  - Drafts (Folders 11.14 - 11.15)
  - Drafts (Folder 19.04)
  - Drafts (Folder M4 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials — Negatives (Folder 3.11)
  - Published Materials (Folder 3.12)
  - Published Prints (Folder M3 (Oversize))
  - Published Prints (Folder M18 (Oversize))
- SERIES IV. ANNAPOLIS, MD
  - Research and Drafts Materials, Possibly Annapolis or Princeton (Folders 9.01 - 9.05)
  - Published Materials (Folders 11.01)
  - Published Materials (Folder M1 (Oversize))
- SERIES V. DEERFIELD, MA
  - Research Materials – Photographs: Deerfield or Sturbridge Village (Folder 1.18)
  - Drafts (Folder M2 (Oversize))
  - Drafts — Deerfield and Sturbridge Village (Folder 3.13)
  - Published Prints (Folder M2 (Oversize))
- SERIES VI. BLACKSTONE VALLEY, MA
  - Research Materials (Folders 6.01 - 6.02)
  - Research Materials (Folders 13.11 - 13.13)
  - Drafts (Folder 13.14)
  - Drafts (Folder M19 (Oversize))
  - Published material, 1988 (Folder M19 (Oversize))
- SERIES VII. HINGHAM, MA
  - Published Print, signed by [Rosalind Howe], 1980 (Folder M14 (Oversize))
- SERIES VIII. NANTUCKET, MA
  - Drafts (Folder 7.07)
  - Drawing (Folders 15.09)
- SERIES IX. PRINCETON, MA
  - Research Materials (Folders 4.07 – 4.10)
  - Research Materials – Photographs (Folders 1.07 - 1.09)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folder 12.03)
  - Research and Drafts Materials, Possibly Annapolis or Princeton (Folders 9.01 - 9.05)
  - Drafts (Folders 4.11 – 4.21)
  - Drafts (Folders 12.04 - 12.11)
  - Drafts (Folders 12.14 - 12.20)
  - Drafts (Folder 19.05)
  - Drafts (Folder M14 (Oversize))
  - Drawings (Folders 5.01 - 5.03)
  - Drawings (Folders 13.01 - 13.04)
  - Drawings (Folder M17 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials (Folders 5.04 - 5.05)
  - Published Materials (Folders 13.05 - 13.07)
  - Published Materials (Folders 19.06 - 19.08)
  - Original pencil drawing (Folder M7 (Oversize))
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder 19.09)
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder M7 (Oversize))
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder M12 (Oversize))
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder M13 (Oversize))
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder M14 (Oversize))
- SERIES X. STURBRIDGE VILLAGE, MA
  - Research Materials – Photographs: Deerfield or Sturbridge Village (Folder 1.18)
  - Drafts (Folder 13.15)
  - Drafts — Deerfield and Sturbridge Village (Folder 3.13)
  - Published Materials (Folder 6.03)
  - Published Materials (Folder 13.16)
- SERIES XI. WESTMINSTER, MA
  - Drawings (xeroxes) (Folder 6.18)
- SERIES XII. WORCESTER, MA
  - Research Materials (Folders 11.02 - 11.03)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folder 11.04)
  - Drafts (Folders 11.05 - 11.09)
  - Drafts (Folder 12.21)
  - Drafts (Folder 19.01)
  - Draft (Folder M5 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials (Folders 3.02 - 3.04)
  - Published Materials (Folder 19.02)
  - Published Print (Folder M3 (Oversize))
- SERIES XIII. CATHEDRAL VILLAGE, Philadelphia, PA (senior living facility)
  - Research Materials - Photographs (Folders 1.01 - 1.06)
  - Research Materials – Photographs (Folder 1.10)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folder 5.09)
  - Drafts (Folders 5.10 - 5.19)
  - Drafts (Folders 13.09 - 13.10)
  - Published Materials (Folder 5.20)
  - Published Materials (Folder 14.18)
  - Published Materials, photocopies (Folder 14.19)
- SERIES XIV. CHESTNUT HILL, PA
  - Research Materials (Folder 6.04)
  - Research Materials - Photographs (Folders 1.11 - 1.17)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folders 6.05 - 6.06)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folder 6.17)
  - Research Materials and Drafts (Folders 14.02 - 14.03)
  - Drafts (Folders 6.08 - 6.10)
  - Drafts (Folder 14.01)
  - Drafts (Folders 14.04 - 14.08)
  - Drafts — Negatives (Folder 6.07)
  - Drafts and photocopies (Folders 14.09 - 14.11)
  - Drafts—Plates Commissioned by VC (Folder 14.12)
  - Drafts, mostly Chestnut Hill, includes Rittenhouse Town (Folders 14.13 - 14.17)
  - Drafts and Published Materials (Folder 19.10)
  - Drawings (Folder 6.11)
  - Drawings (Folder M16 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials — Negatives (Folder 6.12)
  - Published Materials (Folders 6.13 - 6.15)
  - Published Materials (Folders 19.11 - 19.14)
  - Published Materials (Folder M16 (Oversize))
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder 6.16)
  - Exhibition Materials (Folders 15.01 - 15.03)
  - Exhibition Materials (Folder 19.05)
- SERIES XV. PHILADELPHIA, PA
  - Research Materials (Folder M8 (Oversize))
  - Research Materials (Folder 4.01)
  - Drafts (Folder 4.02)
  - Drafts (Folders 12.01 - 12.02)
  - Drafts (Folder M6 (Oversize))
  - Drawing (Folder 4.03)
  - Published Materials (Folders 4.04 – 4.06)
  - Published Materials (Folder M8 (Oversize))
- SERIES XVI. RITTENHOUSE TOWN, PA
  - Research Materials (Folder 15.10)
  - Drafts (Folder 15.11)
  - Drafts, mostly Chestnut Hill, includes Rittenhouse Town (Folders 14.13 - 14.17)
  - Published Materials (Folder 7.08)
  - Published Materials (Folder 15.12)
- SERIES XVII. UP COUNTRY PENNSYLVANIA
  - Research Materials — Photographs (Folder 1.19)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Bethlehem Pike (Folder 1.20)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Sumneytown Pike, Limekilm Pike, Harleysville Pike (Folder 1.21)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Skippack Pike (Folders 1.22 - 1.23)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Ridge Pike (Folder 1.24)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — De Kalb Pike (Folder 1.25)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Germantown Pike (Folder 1.26)
  - Drafts — Sumneytown Pike, Limekilm Pike, Harleysville Pike (Folder 7.01)
  - Drafts — Germantown Pike (Folder 7.02)
  - Drafts — Ridge Pike (Folder 7.03)
  - Drafts — De Kalb Pike (Folder 7.04)
  - Drafts — Skippack Pike (Folder 7.05)
  - Drafts — Bethlehem Pike (Folder 7.06)
  - Drafts (Folders 15.04 - 15.05)
  - Drawings (Folders 15.06 - 15.08)
- SERIES XVIII. Rhode Island
  - Research Materials (Folders 7.09 - 7.11)
  - Research Materials (Folders 13.11 - 13.13)
  - Research Materials — Photographs (Folder 1.27)
  - Research Materials — Providence (Folder 5.07)
  - Drafts — Bristol (Folder 13.08)
  - Drafts — Providence (Folder 12.13)
  - Drawings — Rhode Island, including Bristol (Folder 7.12)
  - Drafts — Blackstone Valley, Rhode Island (Folder M2 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials — Bristol (Folder 13.08)
  - Published Materials — Bristol, 1955 (Folder M9 (Oversize))
  - Published Print — Newport, 1957 (Folder M4 (Oversize))
  - Published Materials — Providence (Folder 5.08)
  - Published Materials — Providence, 1962 (Folder M9 (Oversize))
- SERIES XIX. NOTEBOOKS
  - Volumes 1-14 (Box 18)
  - Materials removed from notebook 4 (Folder 7.13)
  - Materials removed from notebook 7 (Folder 7.14)
  - Materials removed from notebook 8 (Folder 7.15)
  - Materials removed from notebook 9 (Folder 7.16)
  - Materials removed from notebook 10 (Folder 7.17)
  - Materials removed from notebook 12 (Folder 7.18)
- SERIES XX. MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS
  - Art Anatomy Materials, Vassar Class, circa 1928 (Folders 8.05 - 8.07)
  - Drawings (Folders 9.16 - 9.20)
  - Drawings (Folders 16.02 - 16.07)
  - Drawings (Folders 20.02 - 20.03)
  - Drawings and Sketches (Folder M15 (Oversize))
  - Figure Studies (Folder M11 (Oversize))
  - Final Drawing, February 1999 (Folder 9.21)
  - Materials relating to the Inauguration of President W. J. Clinton, 1993 (Folder 8.01)
  - Medium Studies (Folders 9.11 - 9.13)
  - Paintings (Folder 20.04)
  - Professional Correspondence and Copyright Material (Box 2)
  - Professional Correspondence with the Albany Institute of History and Art (Folder 8.02)
  - Professional Documents (Folders 8.03 - 8.04)
  - Project Materials (Folders 8.08 - 8.09)
  - Published Materials (Folders 10.01 - 10.02)
  - Published Materials — Springside (Folder 10.03)
  - Published Materials — Cards — Some with Correspondence (Folders 10.04 - 10.06)
  - Published Materials about Howe (Folders 20.05 - 20.06)
  - Published Materials which include Howe’s work (Folders 20.07 - 20.08)
  - Published Materials — Articles by Rosalind Howe (Folder 17.01)
  - Published Materials — Unidentified (Folder 17.04)
  - Research and Drafts Materials, Possibly Annapolis or Princeton (Folders 9.01 - 9.05)
  - Research Materials — Photographs — Unidentified (Folders 1.28 - 1.29)
  - Self-Portrait (Folder 20.01)
  - Sketches (Folders 9.06 - 9.10)
  - Sketches and Paintings (Folder 16.01)
  - Sketches of Construction (Folders 8.14 - 8.15)
  - Sketches of Vehicles (Folders 8.13)
  - Small studies (Folders 8.10 - 8.12)
  - Snow Studies (Folders 9.14 - 9.15)
  - Unidentified Drafts (Folders 10.07 - 10.08)
  - Unidentified Drawings (Folders 10.15 - 10.19)
  - Unidentified Drawings (Folders 17.05 - 17.06)
  - Unidentified Sketches (Folders 10.09 - 10.14)
  - Unidentified Sketches (Folders 17.07 - 17.18)
  - Unidentified Sketches (Folders 20.09 - 20.10)
  - Unidentified Sketches (Folder M15 (Oversize))
  - Winter Studies, 1982 (Folders 17.02 - 17.03)
  - Wood block, Jamaica Print (Box 18)